"Diverticulosis Diet: Should Nuts, Seeds,
and Popcorn Be Avoided?"
Diverticulosis involves
abnormal outpouchings
from the wall of our colon,
affecting most people
by the time
they reach their 60s
whether they know it or not.
In as many as 10 to 25 percent
of individuals
these outpouchings
can become inflamed
and turn the diverticulosis
into diverticulitis,
resulting in hundreds
of thousands of ER visits
and hospitalizations
and, sometimes, even leading
to perforation of the colon,
which may have a fatality rate
as high as one in five.
But it wasn't always like this.
Diverticulosis only became
a problem in the 20th century.
What is now a massive epidemic
didn't even start showing up
in medical textbooks
until 1920.
Diverticulosis appeared
to be a deficiency disease
of Western civilization.
Just like scurvy is
a deficiency disease
caused by a lack of vitamin C,
diverticulosis may be
a deficiency disease
caused by lack of fiber.
Bowel movements
should be effortless,
but when we don't get enough
fiber-containing foods
in our diet,
like whole grains and beans,
we have to strain to push
unnaturally firm stools.
The pressure necessary to force
along small, hard stools
may essentially blow pouches
out of the wall of our colon
like when you squeeze
one of those gel stress balls.
As we got better and better
at refining grains
and stripping away the fiber,
diverticulosis rates
shot up to epidemic levels.
What about populations
like those in rural Africa
where they were eating up
to the triple digit grams a day
that we, as a species,
were meant to get
based on Paleolithic
diet estimates
and paleopoo fossilized feces?
Diverticulosis remained
almost completely absent
in areas that continued
to center their diets
around whole plant foods,
the only foods where fiber
is found in abundance.
So, just like heart disease
is the number one killer
in the United States
and was virtually unknown
in rural Africa,
diverticulosis was
also virtually unknown;
whereas it's the most common
disease of the colon here
and around
the Westernized world.
Migration studies prove
it's not some genetic
racial difference either.
The prevalence
of diverticulosis
was one percent in Japan.
At the same time,
it was 50 times higher
in Japanese people
who started eating
and living like Americans.
Higher fiber intake
may also explain why vegetarians
may be up to nearly three times
less likely
to be affected
by this condition.
Today, increasing fiber intake
is accepted
as the overriding
dietary recommendation
for people afflicted
with diverticulosis,
but what about
the common advice from doctors
telling patients
with the condition
not to eat nuts, seeds,
and corn?
The rationale was that
these foods could get lodged
in one
of the outpouching pockets
and trigger inflammation,
but the myth that we should
avoid eating nuts, corn,
popcorn, and seeds to prevent
episodes like diverticulitis
has been debunked
with modern data.
In fact, Harvard researchers
looked into this
and actually found
protective associations
between nut
and popcorn consumption
and the risk of diverticulitis.
So, doctors should be telling
patients with diverticulosis
that they can eat nuts, corn,
and popcorn without fear,
advice echoed by Harvard,
by the Mayo Clinic,
and the Cleveland Clinic,
where the avoidance advice
was identified
as the number one myth.
A healthy, high-fiber diet
is actually the best medicine
against diverticulitis,
and nuts and seeds
certainly fit the bill.
In fact, increasing
dietary fiber intake
should be seen
as a major public health issue
that may have
a dramatic beneficial effect
in diet-related diseases
and deaths, in general.
In other words,
eat more plants.